Joel Pinheiro

Software Engineer

joelpinheiro.github.io | +351 910 399 321 | joelcoelhopinheiro@gmail.com

Summary

Hello, I'm a **Software Engineer** from Porto, Portugal. I'm currentlyworking at **Blip** as **big data engineer** on the backend side. I spend most of my time **designing** and **developing** awesome projects. I define myself as a **full stack engineer** with know how of software **architecture**, **scalability** and **performance**. I am able to adapt to **multicultural environments**, gained through several **experiences abroad**. My main interests are **Security**, **Big Data**, **Machine Learning**, **Trading** and **Web**.

Work History

Big Data Engineer

Blip.pt

Project: Betfair system for processing real-time streaming data with amassive scalability, distributed and fault-tolerant/fail fast recovery systems. **Technologies**: big data techs such as Kafka, Cassandra, Storm, Redis, Zookeeper using Java or Scala programming.

Software Engineer Sep 2016 - Oct 2017

Consultant @ ING Bank & BNP Paribas (Brussels)

Project: Online Leasing Solution & Reporting Tool. **Technologies**: Java 8, Spring Boot, Spring Security, GWT, Hibernate/JPA, JavaScript (ECMA5), Unit/Integration Tests, Maven, Nexus, Jenkins, Git + GitLab.

Researcher Apr 2015 - Jan 2016

Instituto de Telecomunicações

Project: IoT Decentralised Framework. **Technologies**: JavaScript (ECMA 5 / 6), TypeScript, HTML5 tools such as WebRTC, web threads (WebWorkers), UnitTests, Gulp.

Software Engineer 2014 - 2014

FIS, Amsterdam (Netherlands)

Project: Online Banking Solution for Harrods Bank. **Technologies**: Java Enterprise (Struts, Spring), Tomcat, GTM Database and Web Development.

Java Developer 2009 - 2011

CA Informática - Credito Agricola, Lisbon (Portugal)

Application: Calypso (financial solution - Java Web Start Application) Projects: Foreign Exchange, Bonds, Bloomberg Interface **Technologies**: Java, Oracle Database 10g, Microsoft Visual SourceSafe, WSDL.

Education

Bachelor & Master's in Computer and Telematics Engineering

2011 - 2016

University of Aveiro

Favorite Courses: Operating Systems, Algorithms And Complexity, Programming I-III, Computer Architecture, Data Bases, Network Architecture, Security, Distributed Systems, Concurrent Programming and Audio And Video Coding.

Projects Portfolio / Open Source Software

iTrading (Side Project): joelpinheiro.github.io/itrading

Github Repository: github.com/joelpinheiro

Skills

Java

Six years of experience. Three years of enterprise level experience and three more in university. This is the language I feel most comfortable to use in order to solve any problem. **Currently studying to be a Java 8 certified developer.**

Javascript

Oct 2017 - Now

Two years of experience. Highly used on professional/academic projects.

Python

One year of experience. Academic experience and some side projects. Take a look at Projects Portfolio section.

C/C++

Academic experience. Take a look at Projects Portfolio section.

Scala

Currently doing the Martin Odersky' Scala specialisation of Coursera.

Techs/Frameworks

NodeJS, Spring, GWT, CherryPy, Atom Shell (Electron), JAX-RS/Jetty, Express, Socket.io, Django, Angular.JS, JQuery, Meteor.JS, D3, Hibernate/JPA.

Tools

Docker, NGINX, Chef, Vagrant, Puppet, Ansible, Jenkins, Maven.

Certifications

- Java SE 8 Oracle Certified Professional
- **Scrum Master** Accredited Certification by Scrum Institute
- **Principles of functional programming in Scala** by Martin Odersky (Coursera)